<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "http://fgdc.gov/metadata/fgdc-std-001-1998.dtd">
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>USDA Forest Service</origin>
        <pubdate>November 1, 2019</pubdate>
        <title>Average Temperature, 1948-1968</title>
        <geoform>raster digital data</geoform>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>TopoWx (“Topography Weather”) temperature data were used to compare historical temperature for two time periods; this dataset provides improved historical temperature data, as compared with other gridded temperature datasets. This dataset represents the average temperature between 1948 and 1968 for the contiguous United States. For more information about TopoWx, see http://www.scrimhub.org/resources/topowx/.</abstract>
      <purpose>Average temperature between 1948 and 1968 for the contiguous U.S.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>1948</begdate>
          <enddate>1968</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Publication Date</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-125.004167</westbc>
        <eastbc>-66.670834</eastbc>
        <northbc>51.195833</northbc>
        <southbc>24.1125</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
        <themekey>environment</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>USDA Forest Service</themekey>
        <themekey>USFS</themekey>
        <themekey>Office of Sustainability and Climate</themekey>
        <themekey>OSC</themekey>
        <themekey>climate</themekey>
        <themekey>temperature</themekey>
        <themekey>TopoWx</themekey>
        <themekey>800 meters</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>The USDA Forest Service makes no warranty, expressed or implied, including the
            warranties of merchantability and fitness for a particular purpose, nor assumes any
            legal liability or responsibility for the accuracy, reliability, completeness or utility
            of these geospatial data, or for the improper or incorrect use of these geospatial data.
            These geospatial data and related maps or graphics are not legal documents and are not
            intended to be used as such. The data and maps may not be used to determine title,
            ownership, legal descriptions or boundaries, legal jurisdiction, or restrictions that
            may be in place on either public or private land. Natural hazards may or may not be
            depicted on the data and maps, and land users should exercise due caution. The data are
            dynamic and may change over time. The user is responsible to verify the limitations of
            the geospatial data and to use the data accordingly.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>USFS Chief Information Office, Enterprise Data Warehouse</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <city>Washington</city>
          <state>DC</state>
          <postal>20250</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>Please send an e-mail to the address below.</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>SM.FS.data@usda.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>USDA Office of Sustainability and Climate and the Rocky Mountain Research
            Station</datacred>
    <native> Version 6.2 (Build 9200) ; Esri ArcGIS 10.5.1.7333</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic/>
    <complete>Data is complete as of publication.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Horizontal accuracy is variable.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>According to the project website (http://www.scrimhub.org/resources/topowx/), "The objective of TopoWx is to provide gridded temperature estimates that accurately capture both (1) locally relevant topoclimate spatial patterns; and (2) regional climate variability and trends. TopoWx gridded temperature estimates are based on historical daily station observations, digital elevation model (DEM) variables, atmospheric reanalysis data, and MODIS land skin temperature. Interpolation procedures include moving window regression kriging and geographically weighted regression. To better ensure temporal consistency, all input station observations are homogenized using the GHCN/USHCN Pairwise Homogenization Algorithm." Monthly temperature data were downloaded as netCDF files from the TopoWx website (https://download.scrim.psu.edu/TopoWx/release_2017-07/monthly/). Additional processing was applied to do the following: a) for each year, all the maximum monthly temperature files were averaged together, then all the minimum monthly datasets, b) the average annual minima and maxima were averaged together, to create an overall annual average, c) these datasets were exported as rasters, then d) the annual averages were averaged together to produce an overall average for the time period of interest. R scripts were used for the first three steps, and a Python script for the fourth.</procdesc>
        <procdate>2019</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Raster</direct>
    <rastinfo>
      <rasttype>Pixel</rasttype>
      <rowcount>3250</rowcount>
      <colcount>7000</colcount>
    </rastinfo>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <geograph>
        <latres>8.983152841195215e-009</latres>
        <longres>8.983152841195215e-009</longres>
        <geogunit>Decimal Degrees</geogunit>
      </geograph>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D WGS 1984</horizdn>
        <ellips>WGS 1984</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Raster</enttypl>
        <enttypd>A spatial data model that defines space as an array of equally sized cells
                    arranged in rows and columns, and composed of single or multiple bands. Each
                    cell contains an attribute value and location coordinates. Unlike a vector
                    structure, which stores coordinates explicitly, raster coordinates are contained
                    in the ordering of the matrix. Groups of cells that share the same value
                    represent the same type of geographic feature.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Esri GIS Dictionary</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Value</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Average annual temperature in degrees Celsius</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Forest Service</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Degrees Celsius</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>USFS Chief Information Office, Enterprise Data Warehouse</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <city>Washington</city>
          <state>DC</state>
          <postal>20250</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>Please send an e-mail to the address below.</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>SM.FS.data@usda.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>The U.S. Forest Service makes no warranty, express or implied, nor assumes any
            liability or responsibility for the accuracy, reliability, completeness, or utility of
            these geospatial data or for the improper or incorrect use of those data. The data are
            dynamic and may change over time. The user is responsible for verifying the limitations
            of the geospatial data and for using the data accordingly.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20191101</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>USFS Chief Information Office, Enterprise Data Warehouse</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <city>Washington</city>
          <state>DC</state>
          <postal>20250</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>Please send an e-mail to the address below.</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>SM.FS.data@usda.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    <mettc>local time</mettc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
