<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "http://fgdc.gov/metadata/fgdc-std-001-1998.dtd">
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>USDA Forest Service</origin>
        <pubdate>November 1, 2019</pubdate>
        <title>Date of Thaw, Historical</title>
        <geoform>raster digital data</geoform>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>The National Forest Climate Change Maps project provides information on projected climate changes at a scale relevant to decision-making process, including forest plans to meet the needs of national forest managers. The maps use the best available science and are available for every national forest with relevant data coverage. The datasets include variables related to precipitation and air temperature, for both historical data and future projections. These datasets were created using 20-model averages of downscaled climate data from MACA-v2METDATA (https://climate.northwestknowledge.net/MACA/). For more information about this project, see https://www.fs.fed.us/rm/boise/AWAE/projects/national-forest-climate-change-maps.html. This dataset represents the average date of thaw (that is, the first day that temperatures do not drop below zero at the beginning the annual frost-free season), for the historical time period (1975-2005), for the contiguous United States.</abstract>
      <purpose>Average date of thaw for the historical time period (1975-2005) for the contiguous U.S.</purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>1975</begdate>
          <enddate>2005</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>Publication Date</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>None planned</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-124.792997</westbc>
        <eastbc>-67.042997</eastbc>
        <northbc>49.416856</northbc>
        <southbc>25.041856</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>ISO 19115 Topic Categories</themekt>
        <themekey>environment</themekey>
      </theme>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>USDA Forest Service</themekey>
        <themekey>USFS</themekey>
        <themekey>Office of Sustainability and Climate</themekey>
        <themekey>OSC</themekey>
        <themekey>climate</themekey>
        <themekey>temperature</themekey>
        <themekey>frost</themekey>
        <themekey>growing season</themekey>
        <themekey>date of thaw</themekey>
        <themekey>0.041666667 degrees</themekey>
      </theme>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>The USDA Forest Service makes no warranty, expressed or implied, including the
            warranties of merchantability and fitness for a particular purpose, nor assumes any
            legal liability or responsibility for the accuracy, reliability, completeness or utility
            of these geospatial data, or for the improper or incorrect use of these geospatial data.
            These geospatial data and related maps or graphics are not legal documents and are not
            intended to be used as such. The data and maps may not be used to determine title,
            ownership, legal descriptions or boundaries, legal jurisdiction, or restrictions that
            may be in place on either public or private land. Natural hazards may or may not be
            depicted on the data and maps, and land users should exercise due caution. The data are
            dynamic and may change over time. The user is responsible to verify the limitations of
            the geospatial data and to use the data accordingly.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>USFS Chief Information Office, Enterprise Data Warehouse</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <city>Washington</city>
          <state>DC</state>
          <postal>20250</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>Please send an e-mail to the address below.</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>SM.FS.data@usda.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <datacred>USDA Office of Sustainability and Climate and the Rocky Mountain Research
            Station</datacred>
    <native> Version 6.2 (Build 9200) ; Esri ArcGIS 10.5.1.7333</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>No formal attribute accuracy tests were conducted.</attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic/>
    <complete>Data is complete as of publication.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Horizontal accuracy is variable.</horizpar>
      </horizpa>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Daily temperature data was downloaded as netCDF files from MACAv2METDATA (http://thredds.northwestknowledge.net:8080/thredds/reacch_climate_CMIP5_macav2_catalog2.html) for each of 20 general circulation models (GCMs). R scripts were used to a) download the data, b) open each netCDF file, then for each year in this file, find the maximum number of consecutive days with a minimum temperature above freezing, and then find the first day of this frost-free period; this corresponds to the date of thaw, c) average these values for all years of the historical time period, d) average the values for all 20 models, and e) export these results as a raster.</procdesc>
        <procdate>2019</procdate>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Raster</direct>
    <rastinfo>
      <rasttype>Pixel</rasttype>
      <rowcount>585</rowcount>
      <colcount>1386</colcount>
    </rastinfo>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <geograph>
        <latres>8.983152841195215e-009</latres>
        <longres>8.983152841195215e-009</longres>
        <geogunit>Decimal Degrees</geogunit>
      </geograph>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D WGS 1984</horizdn>
        <ellips>WGS 1984</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257223563</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <eainfo>
    <detailed>
      <enttyp>
        <enttypl>Raster</enttypl>
        <enttypd>A spatial data model that defines space as an array of equally sized cells
                    arranged in rows and columns, and composed of single or multiple bands. Each
                    cell contains an attribute value and location coordinates. Unlike a vector
                    structure, which stores coordinates explicitly, raster coordinates are contained
                    in the ordering of the matrix. Groups of cells that share the same value
                    represent the same type of geographic feature.</enttypd>
        <enttypds>Esri GIS Dictionary</enttypds>
      </enttyp>
      <attr>
        <attrlabl>Value</attrlabl>
        <attrdef>Date of thaw: average date at which daily minimum temperature rises above freezing, at the start of the longest number of consecutive non-freezing days</attrdef>
        <attrdefs>U.S. Forest Service</attrdefs>
        <attrdomv>
          <udom>Day of year</udom>
        </attrdomv>
      </attr>
    </detailed>
  </eainfo>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>USFS Chief Information Office, Enterprise Data Warehouse</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <city>Washington</city>
          <state>DC</state>
          <postal>20250</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>Please send an e-mail to the address below.</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>SM.FS.data@usda.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <distliab>The U.S. Forest Service makes no warranty, express or implied, nor assumes any
            liability or responsibility for the accuracy, reliability, completeness, or utility of
            these geospatial data or for the improper or incorrect use of those data. The data are
            dynamic and may change over time. The user is responsible for verifying the limitations
            of the geospatial data and for using the data accordingly.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20191101</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>USFS Chief Information Office, Enterprise Data Warehouse</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>physical</addrtype>
          <city>Washington</city>
          <state>DC</state>
          <postal>20250</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>Please send an e-mail to the address below.</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>SM.FS.data@usda.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    <mettc>local time</mettc>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>
